so let's talk about the optimal way to
engage in activities or to consume
things that evoke dopamine how are we
supposed to engage with these dopamine
evoking activities in ways that are
healthy and beneficial for us how do we
achieve these Peaks which are so Central
to our well-being and experience of life
without dropping our Baseline and the
key lies in intermittent release of
dopamine the real key is to not expect
or chase high levels of dopamine release
every time we engage in these activities
now the smartphone is a very interesting
tool for dopamine in light of all this
it's extremely common nowadays to see
people texting and doing selfies and
communicating in various ways listening
to podcasts listening to music doing all
sorts of things while they engage in
other activities or going to dinner and
texting other people or Mak plan sharing
information that's all wonderful it
gives depth and richness and color to
life but it isn't just about our
distracted nature when we're engaging
with the phone it's also a way of
layering in dopamine and it's no
surprise that levels of depression and
lack of motivation are really on the
increase there's something called
dopamine reward prediction error when we
expect something to happen we are highly
motivated to pursue it
if it happens great we get the reward
the reward comes in various chemical
forms including dopamine and we are more
likely to engage in that behavior again
this is the basis of casino gambling
this is how they keep you going back
again and again and again even though on
average the house really does win
everything that we've talked about until
now sets up an explanation or an
interpretation of why interacting with
digital technology can potentially lead
to disruption are lowering in Baseline
levels of dopamine there's a
intermittent schedule by which dopamine
sometimes arrives sometimes a little bit
sometimes a lot sometimes a medium
amount okay that intermittent
reinforcement schedule is actually the
best schedule to export to other
activities how do you do that well first
of
all if you are engaged in activities
School sport relationship Etc where you
experience a win you should be very
careful about allowing yourself to
experience huge peaks in dopamine unless
you're willing to suffer the the crash
that
follows and waiting a period of time for
it to come back up what would this look
like in the practical sense well let's
say you are somebody who really does
enjoy exercise or let's say you're
somebody who kind of likes exercise but
forces yourself to do it but you make it
pleasureful by giving yourself your
favorite cup of coffee first or maybe
taking a pre-workout drink or taking
taking an energy drink or listening to
your favorite music and then you're in
the gym and you're listening to your
music that all sounds great right well
it is great except that by layering
together all these things to try and
Achieve that dopamine release and by
getting a big peak in dopamine you're
actually increasing the number of
conditions required to achieve pleasure
from that activity again I can use a
personal example for this I happen to
really enjoy working out I've always
really enjoyed it but in recent years I
noticed that if I was bringing my phone
to my workouts then Not only was I a
little bit more distracted and not
focusing on what I was doing as much as
I could have or should have but also I
started to lose interest in what I was
doing it wasn't as pleasureful I would
feel like it just didn't have the same
kind of oomph and I was beginning to
question my
motivation as I started learning more
about this relationship between the
Peaks and the baselines and dopamine
what I realized was that some time ago I
probably experienced a incredible
increase in the amount of dopamine
during one of my workouts because I
enjoy working out and I enjoy listening
to music I also enjoy listening to
podcast I also enjoy communicating with
people those are all wonderful Pursuits
but I had layered in too many of them
too many times and then it essentially
wasn't working for me anymore much in
the same way a drug wouldn't work for
somebody who takes it repeatedly because
their Baseline of dopamine is dropping
so at least for this calendar year I've
made a rule for myself which is I don't
allow my phone into my workouts at all
no music at least not from the phone it
can be in the
room I might listen to a podcast in the
room but I don't listen to anything or
engage in anything on my phone no
texting whatsoever and most of the time
I just don't even bring it with me for
that period of time it's only a short
period of time I'm not training that
often this is something that I think has
been
misinterpreted as people can't be alone
now people talk about oh you know they
can't walk across the street or they
can't go anywhere ride the bus can't be
on the plane without being in contact
they can't handle just their thoughts I
don't think that's really what's going
on I think what's happened is that we
achieved the great dopamine increase
that comes from this incredible thing
which I personally enjoy being able to
communicate by phone by text and
exchange pictures and send links and
these kinds of things social media but
then what happens is it doesn't have
that same fulfilling aspect to it
and it tends to remove the excitement
and the pleasure of the very activities
that we are engaged in so I know this is
a hard one for many people but I do
invite you to try removing multiple
sources of dopamine release or what used
to be multiple sources of dopamine
release from activities that you want to
continue to enjoy or that you want to
enjoy more and now you understand the
biological mechanisms that would underly
a statement like that it takes a little
bit of working with I know it can be
challenging in the first week or so of
not engaging with the phone during any
kind of workout that actually was really
tough but now I'm back to a place where
I enjoy it that much more I also feel as
if I conquered something in terms of the
circuitry related to dopamine I Now
understand why something that I enjoyed
so much had become less pleasureful for
me and there's a deep deep satisfaction
that comes from understanding okay there
wasn't anything wrong with me or the
what I was doing or anything at all it
was just a there was something wrong
with the approach I was taking which was
layering in all these sources of
dopamine and dropping my Baseline if you
want to maintain motivation for school
exercise relationships or Pursuits of
any duration in kind the key thing is to
make sure that the peak and dopamine if
it's very high doesn't occur too often
and if something does occur very often
that you vary how much dopamine you
experience with each engagement in that
activity so do like the casinos do
certainly works for them and four
activities that you would like to
continue to engage in over time whatever
those happen to be start paying
attention to the amount of dopamine and
excitement and pleasure that you achieve
with those and start modulating that
somewhat at random that might be
removing some of the dopamine releasing
chemicals that you might take prior
maybe you remove them every time but
then every once in a while you introduce
them maybe
it involves sometimes doing things
socially that you enjoy doing socially
sometimes doing the same thing but
alone there are a lot of different ways
to do this there are a lot of different
ways to approach this but now knowing
what you know about Peaks and baselines
in dopamine and understanding how
important it is not just to achieve
Peaks but to maintain that Baseline at a
healthy level it should be
straightforward for you to implement
these intermittent schedules
[Music]